Thank you for
patience.
Now, our
first submitter is from BARNZ,
Board of Airline
representatives.
Ms O'Brien.
Is she
coming in on Zoom?
I think Kath should be coming from Zoom.
She's joined us on Zoom.
Oh, here we go.
All right. Ms. O'Brien, welcome. I'm Greg O'Connor.
I'm the chair of the Petitions Committee.
I will just introduce ourselves for you.
We've got the other submitters in the room, so we'll do our introductions now, and
then we'll come back to you on the note.
Andrew Bayly.
Kia ora.
Kia ora. Celia Wade-Brown.
And joining you on Zoom is...
Kia ora, Kath. Greg Fleming, MP for Maungakiekie.
All right.
Kia ora.
Great, that worked. All right. So now welcome, Kath.
You've take your submissions as read, but we'd like to
take us through the highlights, and you've got 10 minutes, so hopefully leave time
for some questions.
Welcome.
Thank you so much. Thank you. And thank you for the opportunity to appear.
I know you have it, but for the record, my name is Kath O'Brien, and I am the
executive director of the Board of Airline Representatives, which
represents airlines flying to New Zealand.
We have sort of 20 to 25 members at any one time, and
that includes airlines that are international, in the
majority, and also our domestic operators in New Zealand,
Qantas, and airlines like Air Chathams.
I don't say that we represent every single airline, but we are the large
majority.
And so
thank you for the opportunity to submit to this petition, and I will take
the submission as read and will not go through every point.
I think
that the sort of key things that I would say is that there
have been some substantial improvements by airlines post the
pandemic recovery period in their operations, and in particular
around their customer reaccommodation in the event of delay and
cancellation. And
I note the petition of Consumer New Zealand,
and I am sure that there are still scenarios
where customer experiences are not what we would wish.
And I think the Consumer New Zealand petition
proposes
a solution that isn't
perfect in terms of using information disclosure regulation.
An information disclosure is something that we use
to monitor
prices at regulated airports, or we use to monitor on-time
performance of airlines as the Ministry of Transport
publishes. And that regulation isn't particularly
suitable for a solution for this problem.
But happily
we do have a solution in train. And
in my submission, I noted that there's work underway with the Aviation
Council, of which BARNZ is a member, as are other
members of the aviation system here in New Zealand.
It is led by Minister James Shaw,
and it is housed within the Ministry for Cities, Environment,
Regions and Transport.
So that council
is working on a number of things to improve New Zealand's aviation system, and one
of those is consumer information
in the event of delays and cancellations and that sort of thing.
And
the Aviation Action Plan is publicly available, and the
action relevant to that matter is in that
action plan.
And the publicly available information tells us that
officials have taken advice to Minister Shaw on this matter.
And in fact, in very recent days,
officials have been talking to airlines about a voluntary customer
charter to address some of these challenges
in a way that would improve outcomes for consumers.
And so we're quite a long way down the road on the work that would
sort of put into a framework New Zealand's approach to this.
And so I would just encourage the committee to seek advice from the Ministry for
Cities, Environment, Regions and Transport or indeed Minister
Shaw, and
allow that work to continue as it should, rather than
adding another process that might be duplicitous
on this matter.
Duplicitous, I don't think
Yes. Duplicates anyway. So look, we have just
been advised of that ourselves just before coming to this meeting, I might say,
so that does sort of put something of a
different dimension to where we're coming from. But thank you.
And I apologize, I know I called you BARNZ.
You're not BARNZ because you're-
There is a BARNZ, and they're really good at construction, I think.
Yeah.
But BARNZ is really good at flying planes, so
Yes.
And may never
the twain meet.
Indeed not. I don't think we can build a plane.
Yeah. So all right. Well, any questions,
members for Ms. O'Brien.
Can I ask you two questions, Kath?
I'll come in.
The first thing is
the compensation that you get if you
have a delay on an international flight under Montreal
versus what you get paid out domestically,
are they aligned?
Because often in airports you sort of get the $10 voucher, go and have a cup of
coffee type stuff if you are delayed.
What is the sort of level of compensation, and is that standard across the
airlines?
So the Montreal Convention is
something that airlines have to comply with on their
global networks and, of course, here in New Zealand.
And I don't profess to be an aviation lawyer, so I would
not like to
say exactly how it works.
But I think
here in New Zealand, and in line with the Montreal Convention, we talk
about
matters that are within and outside of the airline's control.
So if there is a weather event, for example, that is outside of the airline's
control and generally does not attract, for example,
compensation to the passenger. What airlines
will do is they will re-accommodate that passenger on the next available service if
they can and that sort of thing. And we've seen a lot of that,
for example, when Auckland Airport flooded substantially,
airlines worked really hard to re-accommodate those passengers even where they
might not have had to. So I think airlines will go above
sometimes what international conventions will otherwise dictate.
Okay. So the question of the timing, and you raise it twice in your
report, and you do list them,
there are clearly issues that the airline
is responsible for.
Yes.
You
don't have a crew turn up. You have an engine breakdown.
Those
you don't have to wait. And you talk about having to
come to a firm view on where liability
sits for a delay. Where it's evident and obvious
that it is the airline, for instance, as opposed to
someone on a ground handling service whacking into the side of the
plane. It happened in Wellington once with me.
At that situation, do airlines automatically pay
out and compensate and make people aware?
Or that's where I think the way you wrote
your report, it was very unclear about when there was clear liability
and people were sitting in the airport as opposed to, oh, well, I don't know,
if it's fog related or something like that, then that's a different issue, right?
Is it-
Yeah.
I think that
when the matter is within the airline's control, the most important thing that the
airline is going to try and do immediately is actually get the customer
where they wish to go. So they won't, for example,
refund the customer and leave them stranded wherever they are and let them go off
and buy a new ticket because that isn't getting the customer the service that they
actually want, which is the travel.
So in the first instance, airlines will do all they can to get the
customer where they need to go as soon as possible.
And where that's not possible, and the delay or the disruption is within the
airline's control, then that is something that airlines
will give the customer options for refund or credit
or travel on another service. Those other options
then roll out. But the first thing is always, can we get the customer where they
want to go?
All right. Thank you.
All right. See you there. Greg Fleming, sorry.
Well, kia ora ano. Kath, thank you for that.
Just when I look at the Commerce Commission's
investigation and ruling into Jetstar's
challenges a couple of years ago, obviously they're pretty significant.
Do you have confidence that a voluntary
charter is going to be adhered to?
Look, I think actually it is the best and most
pragmatic way that New Zealand could
make quick progress
to be clear about what it expects from its
aviation system participants. I think one of the challenges that we've got at
the moment is that there are a lot of complex
frameworks emerging around the world, and they are
generating very sort of perverse and
unintended outcomes with a lot more delay and difficulty in
progressing complaints. And I think that actually if we wanted
to have a sort of sensible run at this,
having a voluntary charter is a great first step.
And then if that
is not working, then we can look at more difficult
and frankly more costly solutions.
But actually, this is a really sensible first step.
Okay. And I guess there's the
make it clear to the airlines that
what you just outlined is the process-
Yeah. I think it will be important
... which, again, is a pretty good incentive as well to
follow the charter.
Yeah, look, for sure. And I think it's really important to work with airlines, and
indeed consumer groups to understand the concerns and
make sure that what we do design meets the need.
And so it will be important to have a consultation process on this work, which
we're not quite up to. And I guess my plea to this committee
is to sort of allow for that process to continue because we are quite advanced
and not add to another step somewhere else.
Yeah.
Susie White-Brown.
Thank you very much.
Having experienced a recent two-day delay
coming back to this country,
one of the issues is the communication with the customer.
It was not clear.
If English hadn't been my first language, I don't think
I would have had a clue what was going on, frankly.
The representative at the airport came and
talked to small groups, different groups, different people in different
queues. It was
absolutely appalling.
And
in fact, being fairly
sure of our rights as we tend to be in this-
role. We did get our accommodation, and
taxi, and food, and so on, all reimbursed very nicely and
quickly. And presumably, we got on the first flight available.
But it was not clear as to whether people should be looking to rebook
themselves or to... So all I'm saying is that
the international regime is not
particularly good for the customer either.
So
I think it's not only about the compensation, it's about
who's making what efforts to get people rebooked.
I agree that airlines want to get you on the next flight.
I think, yeah.
It's just how the communication is done, as
well as what the actual
entitlements are,
if we dare to use such a word in this house,
would be helpful. Now, that was coming from overseas to
here. I've not had great problems in this country.
But
I would like to also think about if we start with this
voluntary code of practice.
In my view, a
parallel process needs to be very clear as to whether it's being adhered
to or not. Rather than us sitting, well, it won't be me,
sitting here
in five years' time saying, "Well, we had a voluntary code, and we don't really
know how well it's worked."
Okay. I think, yeah.
All right. Okay. I think a bit to go away, unless you want to reply to that,
Kath.
No, I would just, I guess, reflect the complexity of the international
system,
the challenges with local ground handlers
in country. So for example, if a New Zealand carrier was
flying overseas, they are likely to have a foreign company operating
on the ground for them and explaining to their customers.
So more that airlines can do, as I know Air New Zealand has recently announced,
to allow customers to self-serve some of that recovery
themselves in the app and things like that.
That's great, but I do acknowledge the international system
is complex. There are many players, there are many ground handlers, and also
we've got the challenge of travel agents who often make bookings and
have their customer contacts, in effect, as the customer contact.
So when the airline reaches out to re-accommodate a customer-
Mm
... they bump into the travel agent.
It is difficult, and we're constantly trying to improve that.
It is one of the very greatest complexities of aviation.
Absolutely.
All right.
Thank you for that.
All right. Thank you. All right, thank you.
You're welcome to remain on as we now have
aviation industry.
Mr. Wallace, nice to see you again.
Thank you, Mr. Chair.
I'm probably going to sound very similar to Kath, but from a
domestic perspective.
Mm.
Good.
So look, I won't go through my submission,
but we represent
commercial aviation in New Zealand.
So Air New Zealand is a member of ours, but so are most of the regional
airlines.
But our membership encompasses the wider commercial aviation sector in New Zealand,
so tourism flight operators, flight training schools,
aviation engineers, agricultural aviation.
So we cover what's known as general
aviation, but the regional airlines and Air New Zealand are part of
our membership.
I just want to acknowledge the concerns of Consumer New Zealand and their petition.
I think
a number of the concerns are valid, but as Kath has said, and
I'm on the Aviation Council as well,
as we speak, we have a process going through the
Aviation Council
that is looking at the rights of passengers, that is looking at the rights of
consumers, and one of those things is a voluntary charter.
Now, I've talked to my members about a voluntary charter, so I've talked to Air New
Zealand, I've talked to Air Chathams, I've talked to some of the other regional
airlines. And frankly, it would be churlish if they
weren't part of a voluntary charter, and they're prepared to
sign up to a voluntary charter.
Their only reticence is about something that imposes more
costs.
So that's what we have to be very careful of in terms of the regional
airlines.
Mm.
I think Consumer New Zealand in their presentation a few weeks ago said that the
fuel crisis was something in control of airlines. It certainly is not.
And many of
our regional airlines are really, really struggling, as you know, and have
rationalized routes, have cut routes.
And the last thing we want to do, frankly, is put more cost onto them
through a change in the act, through a change in the Section 410 of the Civil
Aviation Act, that would put more cost on them
in terms of the regulatory burden they need to meet.
So I guess what we're saying is,
yeah, let's look at the voluntary charter.
We've got airlines that are prepared to sign up to it.
We've got the process going through the Aviation Council
now. And I'd like to think that whatever happens in the election, that the
Aviation Action Plan will carry over to
a new government, because
everything in there is valid.
The other thing I wanted to say is that
I talked with Air Chathams, who is one of our good members.
And you were just talking before about some of the delays that passengers
experience. And
obviously weather is completely out of control of an airline,
but things like engineering,
staff not turning up, crew not turning up, that is the
responsibility of the airline.
And in the case of Air Chathams, they do everything possible to support
their passengers. A delay of more than 60 to
90 minutes,
they're
offering full refunds, whatever fare the passenger is on.
They're offering refreshments. They're doing everything that's possible.
And that is easier if you're a smaller airline, I must say.
So it is easier if you're a smaller airline to be able to do that.
When you're Air New Zealand, it's not always
obvious to a front
desk staff member, or it's not always known to a front desk staff
member what the cause of that delay is.
So therefore,
the communication can't always be acknowledging
that they're responsible for that delay.
So those things do need to be taken into account.
Recently you would have seen Air New Zealand have just last week actually
introduced the APR, which is the automated passenger
rebooking. Probably it's got more relevance to
international because it will automatically rebook passengers for
delays of more than four hours. So that
is a system that they're now using.
And for pretty simple itineraries, the automatic passenger
rebooking will be able to rebook passengers, the sort of things that you're
talking about,
Celie, with your delay.
Mm.
I think that's probably enough. I'm happy to answer hearts questions, but
I guess I just want to say that
we're acknowledging in the industry that this is a concern.
We're acknowledging Consumer New Zealand's petition, and there is a process
underway to address that.
All right. Questions, members.
Celie.
Yes. And you've just reminded me, I had a day's delay
going to the Chathams. I was in the fortunate situation of having
accommodation there.
It's not so much about the level
of
compensation. I think that's very important, don't get me wrong.
But I think that's relatively clear in that if you're not booked on, and you
need accommodation.
Yes.
It's really about
the commitment in that chart. Have you talked in that charter or in the
development of it about a commitment for clear
communication and making sure that the
customer has received that communication?
And again-
Yeah
... I think there are some complexities about if they've booked through a travel
agent, for sure, and sometimes we have that ourselves with booking
through parliamentary services. I understand that.
But
maybe they need to make sure that they do have the contact details
direct for their passengers. I think there are some questions about that.
Yeah. Look, I don't have all the answers, Celie.
That's the sort of stuff I haven't seen in the voluntary charter that's been
drafted by the ministry. But communication is
definitely a key part of that.
And I think that whole area, all I can say is I think the whole area needs
improvement.
Mm-hmm.
The other thing I'd say is that there is a
Consumer Protections Act. You know about that-
Mm-hmm
... Andrew. And MB administers that.
Arguably, I think, and I put it in my submission-
Mm
... that is something that needs a lot more promotion.
Because most of us wouldn't know to go there.
And the rights of passengers are very clearly spelled out there.
It needs the industry to promote it more, and it actually needs the government to
promote it more.
Mm.
All right. Any other questions, members? All right.
I'll invite the Commerce Commission.
Thank you.
Table.
Thanks, Tom.
Very interesting.
Thanks, you folks.
Tena koutou. My name's Rebecca MacAtamney.
I'm the acting chief executive of the Commerce Commission.
My substantive role is general manager in the Competition and Fair Trading
branch. And I'm joined by my colleague Vicki Conlin who's a senior
investigator in our fair trading team.
So the commission's role in all of this is that we enforce the
Fair Trading Act. So the Fair Trading Act, of course, doesn't require
airlines to give any information to affected passengers.
But what it does require is that any information that is given
is accurate and is not misleading.
And as I think the committee knows, we have taken some action on that
in recent years. We took some enforcement action against Jetstar,
and we are currently investigating Air New Zealand for similar
conduct. So we're really here in your hands to answer any questions you
have. Unfortunately, I cannot give more information about the Air New Zealand
investigation as it is still an active investigation.
However, I can say that we are on track to complete the investigation in
September.
All right.
All right. Mr. Bailey.
Thank you.
Obviously ask you about the first question you posed.
Mm-hmm.
So the act doesn't
require disclosure, which is clearly what this is about.
And then the second thing is you've taken enforcement actions about making sure
it's not misleading. But the first issue, the more central issue, and it's what my
good colleague's been talking about.
So I'm asking from the perspective of the Commerce
Commission, do you believe that there should be a
requirement for disclosure in the act under the
consumer trading? And I'll give you another analogy, is that if you
buy toys for children, they normally have instructions.
So do you have a view that there should be a change, a
legislative change, or?
As a general rule, the commission supports any initiative that is going to
end up with consumers having more and better
information so they understand their rights and can
use that information to enforce those rights.
Whether that is through a change to the legislation or not is probably a question
for M sert.
Okay. So the next question is, you've obviously
taken two prosecution cases
around misleading
issue.
Has your investigation looked at whether in fact-
Under the disclosure that the airlines had made,
were in fact they complied with their own rules around
granting people the issue like a coffee,
whatever. We heard from Mr. Wallace just before.
Has it gone to that second step?
I'll ask Becky to comment on that. Thank you.
Obviously, the Jetstar investigation has been completed and has gone to
prosecution, whereas the Air New Zealand investigation is still underway.
But both of them, we are looking at potential
misrepresentations of the information that they have already provided to
people. So both Air New Zealand and Jetstar already-
Sorry, with all due respect, that's not quite the nuanced question I was
asking. I understand that bit, but my question,
sorry, probably my fault,
is
when you were looking at prosecution of those two parties,
potential whatever,
did you score and did you go and
source what the airlines had said that they would do in a
situation where there was a delay?
And then looked at that and said, well, have they been meeting
that requirement of their disclosed
things that they would do in the event of delay or whatever.
Did they actually deliver the coffee or whatever?
Yeah, that's right.
In the Jetstar investigation, we discovered that Jetstar were not
always honoring what they stated publicly that they would do.
So there's two issues. With Jetstar, they were providing information to
passengers that was not completely in compliance with what
passengers' rights actually were under the Civil Aviation Act and the Montreal
Convention. And then secondly, there were also instances where when
people actually made claims to Jetstar to get reimbursement of the costs that
they had incurred, whether that be the cost of an alternative flight with
Air New Zealand, if Jetstar weren't able to rebook them adequately or the
cost of a hotel.
Jetstar were making misleading representations around particularly the
amounts that people could claim for things like hotels, which went against their
stated information.
All right. Of course, you answered the question.
Just one last observation from you.
You're obviously looking at both airlines, major
airlines. The observation I was going to ask you,
did you see a similarity around the extent
of what compensation both airlines
would offer in event of default? Because the reason I'm asking
this question is that it's been proposed it's this voluntary code, which
hopefully might standardize the response.
But I'm just trying to ask you, in your investigation, did it become
obvious that some airlines, they had a different level of
compensation to the others, or was it reasonably standard?
It's reasonably standard because it's governed by the Civil Aviation
Act and the Montreal Convention. Both of those set out statutory limits for the
amounts that the airlines are liable for.
I guess with Air New Zealand, because the fare tickets are often higher,
the overall level would be higher because it's linked to the cost of the ticket
being 10 times for domestic fares.
But the policies themselves largely reflect what consumers should be
entitled to in law. So it's just reimbursement of costs that they have
incurred up to those statutory limits.
The main issues that we've seen is when people actually try to claim those
costs, how those costs are being assessed by the airlines and subsequently
paid to consumers, and the explanations they're being given for
the amounts that are being offered to them.
Okay.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you. And Mr. Fleming, you've got a question.
Yes. Yeah, tena koutou. I appreciate the question I'm about to ask
will be a difficult one for you guys to answer.
So I'll try and phrase it in a way where you might be able to.
I just I know that this is a question that the petitioner would want me to ask.
Given the behavior that you have seen
from the two airlines, in particular, obviously, Qantas with the prosecution
already so far.
The deliberation that we as a committee are
considering as to whether we recommend a voluntary code
or a mandated one, do you have any advice for
us as to extra things that we might consider
in deciding whether we're being
realistic in landing on a voluntary code as being
effective?
I think that both of those are initiatives that will lead to consumers
having greater levels of information.
So they're both positive outcomes.
Obviously, with regulation, you've got more certainty for consumers.
However, you also have more cost, both for the airlines and for the
regulator, whoever that might end up being.
Right. Thank you.
All right. Look, thank you very much.
What we do now,
having heard from the different parties, we'll prepare a report and recommendation,
obviously taking into account the minister's letter, which we only got
this afternoon ourselves. So thank you very much.
Thank you.
And to our
online. Right. So we now come to next item.
We've got
the ministry, MB.
You like to be referred to as MB or prefer the full name of Business-
MB's fine
...
Innovation and Employment.
All right. Thank you. I think you were here.
I'm sure if you were here we introduced Greg O'Connor, the chair of the committee.
Andrew Beynon. Yeah.
Jenny-May Brown.
And online.
Greg Fleming
She was still upright. It's good.
Yeah.
Thomas.
Shall we, we can introduce ourselves if you like. Get a bit of group here.
So, kia ora koutou. My name's Sian Roguski.
I'm the General Manager, Employment Skills and Immigration Policy, joined
here with Jock Gilray, who's our Deputy Chief Operating
Officer for Immigration New Zealand.
I've got Steve Watson, who's General Manager, Immigration Compliance-
Hi
... and Investigations.
And Sam Foley, who's Manager of the International and Humanitarian
Immigration Policy team.
I think you've got-
We've all come a long way, haven't we, Steve?
So
cops in the Wairarapa.
Yeah.
So thank you for the opportunity to submit, and provide some
evidence.
We didn't necessarily think we would kind of open up with any particular remarks.
I think you've got the information there, and just to maximize time for questions.
But what I thought I would mention, because I realized we didn't relay this
to the clerk of the committee. Depending on where some of
your questions get to, for example, if it starts to get into risk settings or
perhaps some
kind of international relations, they may be some questions that we'd be
happy to answer, but they may be best for a closed session.
So, we'll let you know if it just happens to get there.
All right. So-
All right. So one of the central questions, and I'm going off memory a little
bit,
is
the assertion that Pacific Islanders
don't pose a higher risk than
necessarily other populations. And therefore, I think,
the conclusion is that it seems manifestly
unfair.
How would you respond to that specific assertion?
Yeah. Well, maybe I might just start just talking a little bit about the
general framework that we've set out in the paper around...
Because the core question I think that's raised by the petitioner is
cabinet consideration of whether visa-free status should be-
Yeah
... extended. And as I think as we mentioned,
any advice that is invited from the Minister of Immigration or
other members of Cabinet and that's put forward is around a framework that
sort of dates from about 2015. And as you
mentioned, it has both a kind of risk part of the ledger and a benefits part
of the ledger. Like you say, the risk of overstaying is
one particular element what's on the risk side, but there's also
other things that we'd be looking at as well, regardless of the
country that, or, you know, that we're looking at.
So that includes national security, passport security,
general integrity of the immigration system, what the impact there is.
The external push factors from that particular country, health and
biosecurity. And then on the benefit side of the ledger, we'd absolutely
be looking and advising on the international relationships
at play, trade opportunities, and tourism growth.
So we absolutely sort of recognize that,
in this particular petition, that the issue has been raised about is
the government treating Pacific
countries differently.
That sort of sits within a wider holistic
framework, if you like, of any country that would sort of be put forward.
Okay. That doesn't help me much in terms of answering the question.
So I assume,
on the benefits side-
Mm
... Pacific Islanders play an important role in New Zealand.
So,
the question probably turns on risk assessment and
so
when you are doing the risk assessment,
presumably MBIE does that on your behalf and
informs the minister.
Mm.
So
what
I'm trying to understand, because whether the petitioner's right or wrong, I don't
know. I'm trying to get an... It's an open question to them.
Mm.
That's why it's quite a direct open question.
Yeah.
And I'm trying to understand why is that
assertion, because it
seems to be because it's hard, it must be that assertion.
So going back to that very definite question they asked.
Do Pacific Islanders, are they deemed to be a higher risk category than perhaps
if you come from Germany or America or Britain or China?
Yeah. Why don't you talk to stats?
So one of the ways that we would look at that is through the annual
estimate of overstayers or the unlawful estimate, and I have got
last year's figures. And I think, if I remember
rightly,
Greg Fleming raised when the petition was raised about
the top 10 countries. But there is a second table that
compares the percentages against arrivals.
And Tonga and Samoa are the top two in
terms of the percentage of arrivals who remain unlawfully in New Zealand.
So that would be one thing that we would look at in terms of a risk profile.
So just so what timeframe is that?
That was those arrivals since July
2023 to 30th of June 2025.
Right. And so those two groups represent...
Just could you say that again? That-
So we produce a-
Yeah
... top 10 of numbers. But then
you've got to dig deeper into the data and
put those numbers as a percentage of arrivals.
And Tonga and Samoa and Fiji are in the top four.
Malaysia's third.
So that
is one of the factors that we would use in determining the risk
settings.
Just to sup on that. I
understand the maths, but why does that increase the risk?
I mean, surely it's the total numbers that impact, if they
do, that impact health, education, those
issues that you mentioned. So why do you say
that it's the percentage that matters rather than the crude numbers?
That's a good question.
But-
So we're basing it on country by country
Yeah. By country. Yeah.
Every single country is based on-
I understand that
... a likely pool of risk of the nationalities of that country-
Mm-hmm
... potentially overstaying. So the higher potential
rate of overstaying is a higher potential for those countries.
So when we look at other countries which have a lower rate of overstaying, a bit
less risk overall, although they might have the high numbers of people arriving.
Hmm.
I still don't understand why you are concerned about the percentages of
arrivals than the actual numbers.
We're concerned about both.
About both, yeah. And there are other policy factors that
are taken into consideration in advising the minister.
Question then. Let's just make up a country.
Nirvana is a country-
Oh, no.
... that all of a sudden we have a spike of people coming from
Nirvana that the statistics started to, which
do currently have the visa waiver.
Hmm.
What would trigger
them to have to be then treated in a
similar manner?
Cabinet-
I mean, I think again that comes back where there
is sort of consistent and continually monitoring of the
immigration system and exactly where we're seeing some of those risks come through.
If in our case, Nirvana, was showing this kind of
enhanced risk, that would be something that we would be raising with
ministers. Again, any assessment, for example, of
removal of visa waiver status goes through exactly that same
sort of framework that I outlined.
And I think the last time that advice was tendered and Cabinet made
decisions on that dates back to South Africa, which was
2016 or '15.
Yeah, 2016 they were
removed from visa.
Yeah. Now obviously-
South Africa were removed from-
Correct. Yeah.
Have they been reinstated?
No, they haven't. And you can imagine, and this is why it's a Cabinet
decision. It's quite a decision to go forward and extend a visa waiver.
It's a heck of a decision
to, because again, it plays into those international relations to rescind and take
back a visa waiver status is also obviously a significant sort
of cross-Cabinet decision as well.
Okay. Let's-
Great.
Oh, sorry, Mr. Fleming.
Hmm. Yeah, thank you. You said in your written submission that the
visa waiver was
put in place some 25, 30 years ago, I think.
But after just a few days it was withdrawn
because of concerns around overstaying.
I mean, essentially,
what we've got here is an issue of, it's a lack of trust, isn't it,
from New Zealand to those Pacific countries.
That if we extend the visa waiver,
we're going to have
significant problems with overstaying.
The petitioner's argument to that is
that the overstaying at the moment is a result of the fact
that it's so difficult to get into the country.
So it's essentially a chicken and the egg.
Do you have any comments to that regard?
I mean, I appreciate this is probably outside of your gamut in terms of what you're
able to speak to. But the more I've looked at this issue, the more considered
it both beforehand and through this process, it seems to me that
one side needs to take the first step somehow in terms
of restoring that trust.
I mean, I guess what I would
comment is
that the visa waiver policy does sort of sit within a wider suite of policy
options that ministers have asked for and looked for.
And I think
what we touched upon in the submission is, short of visa waiver,
what are the other things that we can do to kind of take a
step forward towards that space. So that includes the two-year
multi-entry visa that was sort of relatively recently
extended, the reduction in fees,
the sort of escalated
processing in times of urgency, so through funerals.
Hmm.
I absolutely appreciate the petitioner's
views of, well, that doesn't go the full distance, but I think it kind
of reflects that these are sort of
potential steps.
I mean, more broadly, right across government, I think
agencies have relationships and work that they're doing with Pacific
counterparts to absolutely address what are the ways that we
can kind of move forward and address some of the risks that might-
Hmm
... prevent you from going forward.
So that's probably-
Okay. I appreciate that. Can I just ask a follow-up question then?
Because again, you say in your written report you talk about the fact that even
quite... Or, no, it wasn't in there, or it might have been in your introductory
remarks today. You talk about the fact that even as of
last year, there's been concerns around compliance for those
that are coming in. What would be, within your
experience,
for both these countries and all countries, how
long would you need to see
compliance by a country
before serious consideration would be given
to
extending visa waiver?
I mean, ultimately, to be honest, I think that is a question for ministers because
it would be ministers-
Right
... who would request the advice from us and for it to be run through that
framework. That is an advice that we haven't been
asked to put that kind of case to.
Sorry to interrupt, but have you had that experience, between the four of you
involved in this, have
you seen other countries go through that process that have been
off the list and then came to be on the list?
So you gave the example of where South Africa was taken off it.
Have between you, you got some examples of ones that have come on it, on the visa
waiver list?
I don't. Sam, is there anything you would know from history?
Yeah, the most recent ones were the
Seychelles and Mauritius, I want to say.
We'd have to double-check that.
Yeah, we could come back to-
There was also Taiwan. It was about-
Well-
... 13 to 20 years ago we added Taiwan.
Yeah. So just to confirm your question, it's around,
one, that we're on a list, and then I've kind of moved, maybe kind of
come off visa waiver, and then have subsequently reinstated a visa waiver status.
We can provide that answer. I don't know.
Yeah.
We don't have to talk about it here.
It hasn't-
That would be really helpful. Thank you. Yeah.
I'm just basically looking for previous examples of
where we as a country have gone through the process
that the petitioner is asking us to do for their countries. Hmm.
And one final question. Are there any Pacific Island countries that
do have visa waiver?
With New Zealand?
Yeah.
No.
Although
New Caledonia and French Polynesia citizens are French, so they are
part of France, so they can come here-
Okay
... basically as they hold French passports.
And are Pacific countries treated as a
generic group?
No, they would be assessed as individual countries.
So they all-
Yeah
... they are assessed definitely.
And the assurance is that they are assessed as individual countries.
Absolutely.
And-
Yeah
... under that, they all then none of them-
Yes
... not one, other than where there's a citizenship
obligation, not one of them actually qualifies or
meets the criteria for visa waiver.
Except perhaps, were you saying... Yeah. No, that's right.
Except for?
Oh, no, I was thinking about the Seychelles and Mauritius, but that was examples-
Oh, okay
... of where they may have-
French.
Yeah.
And they're French.
Well, I mean-
And so can I just ask, you mentioned Malaysia is on the list with--
is of that same kind of non-compliance as the Pacific nations.
Are they on or off the list?
Malaysia's visa waiver?
Yeah.
Malaysia's visa waiver. In terms of the arrival data, so in terms of the data
that's published, it's the percentage of-
Well, that's really interesting.
So they've got higher incidents of non-compliance than, for example,
Samoa.
Yes.
And yet they are on the-- they are visa waiver list.
No.
Very few.
No, they're in the same camp.
They're third, but in terms of the actual rate of overstaying it's
0.3%.
Yeah.
Versus Tonga is 1.9%.
1.9%.
And Tonga's-
It's around 2%.
5 to 6%. So 5 to 6%.
Yeah.
Oh, I misheard. I thought you said earlier on that Malaysia was up there.
Was it another country you mentioned then or?
Malaysia's in the top three of rates of overstay, but they're not
anywhere near as high as-
Yeah
... Tonga and Samoa.
Yeah. 0.3%.
Okay.
0.9% for Tonga and 0.6% for Samoa.
1.6%, sorry, 1.9%.
Ah, okay. Right. Thank you.
And just there's New Zealanders, as far as you're aware,
aren't subject to visa restrictions anywhere in the
Pacific?
New Zealand citizens.
Of course, we don't regulate New Zealand citizens.
No.
I'd have to have a look.
That was-
Yeah. And obviously, that is a decision for the sovereign
governments of those nations.
Of those nations. Yeah.
Yeah.
All right. Well, thank you. There's-- No. Sorry, were you going to add something?
Never stop anyone. They might add something at the end.
That's some of the best
information gathered. All right.
One quick one.
I just wondered if the
considerations of the historical relationships
between Aotearoa and New Zealand and the Pacific countries-
Mm-hmm
...
to what extent, if any of that-
Mm
... considered in Pacific waiver.
To what extent is Jacinda Ardern's apology for the dawn raids-
Mm-hmm
... considered in
this
measurement of whether overstayers
are problematic or not?
It's a ministerial-
It's a ministerial decision.
It is, and I think-
The decision from-
... I mean, we absolutely would, if we were asked, we would advise, well,
together with our Ministry of Foreign Affairs, that that would absolutely be part
of the relationship.
All of that would be part of that advice.
It's already a part in the benefits assessment.
It is on that side of the ledger. Yeah.
All right. Look, thank you very much. Very enlightening.
And thank you, Nye, for making the trip down
again.